<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Hopes incovragement pointed at in a sermon, preached in St. Margarets Westminster, before the honorable House of Commons, assembled in Parliament: at the last solemn fast, February 28. 1643. by Tho. Young. Published by order of the House of Commons.</title>
            <author>Young, Thomas, 1587-1655.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1644</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 101 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A97297</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing Y92</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E35_18</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R4946</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99872752</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99872752</idno>
            <idno type="VID">154626</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A97297)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 154626)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 6:E35[18])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Hopes incovragement pointed at in a sermon, preached in St. Margarets Westminster, before the honorable House of Commons, assembled in Parliament: at the last solemn fast, February 28. 1643. by Tho. Young. Published by order of the House of Commons.</title>
                  <author>Young, Thomas, 1587-1655.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 38   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>for Ralph Smith, at the sign of the Bible in Cornhill, neere the Royall Exchange.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1644.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: the 4 in the imprint date is crossed out and altered to 1643; "March 8, 1643".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms XXXI, 24 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Fast-day sermons --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:154626:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:154626:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>HOPES INCO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RAGEMENT</hi> pointed at IN A SERMON, PREACHED In <hi>St. Margarets Weſtminſter,</hi> before the Honorable Houſe of <hi>COMMONS,</hi> Aſſembled in PARLIAMENT: At the Laſt Solemn Faſt, <hi>February</hi> 28. 1643.</p>
            <p>BY THO. YOUNG.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Hebr. 6.19.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Which Hope wee have as an anker of the Soule, both ſure and ſtedfaſt, and it entreth into that which is within the vaile.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by Order of the Houſe of Commons.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Printed at <hi>London</hi> for <hi>Ralph Smith,</hi> at the ſigne of the Bible in <hi>Cornhill,</hi> neere the <hi>Royall Exchange.</hi> 1644.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="order">
            <pb facs="tcp:154626:2"/>
            <head>Die Mercurii <hi>28.</hi> Febr. <hi>1643.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>IT is this day ordered by the Commons Houſe of Parliament; That Sr. <hi>John Trever,</hi> &amp; M. <hi>Rous</hi> do from this Houſe give thankes unto Mr. <hi>Young,</hi> for the great paines hee tooke in the Sermon hee preached this day (at the intreaty of the ſaid Commons) at St. <hi>Margarets Weſtminſter,</hi> it being the day of publike Humiliation, and to deſire him to print his Sermon. And he is to have the like priviledge in Printing of his Sermon, as others in the like kinde uſually have had.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>H. Elſynge Cler. Parl. D. Com.</signed> I appoint <hi>Ralph Smith</hi> to print my Sermon. <signed>Tho. Young.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:154626:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>NOBILISSIMIS</hi> EQ<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ITIB<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>S A<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RATIS, <hi>aliiſque Viris prudentiſſimis,</hi> EX Singulis totius REGNI Comitatibus ſelectis, PARL. DOM. COM. Senatoribus honorandis: IN Quorum Solenni conventu inelaborata haec Concio in divae <hi>Margaretae</hi> Templo apud WESTMONASTERIUM</p>
            <p>Solenni jejunioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, die Februarii penultimo fuit habita: eam in Perpetuum demiſſae obſervantiae teſtimonium <hi>L. M. D. D. D.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tho. Young S. Evangelii in Comitatu Suffolcienſi Miniſter.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:154626:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:154626:3"/>
            <head>HOPES-ENCOVRAGEMENT, pointed at IN A SERMON, PREACHED before the Honorable Houſe of <hi>COMMONS.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <hi>GOD having given to his afflicted Church in this diſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted Nation</hi> ſo long cauſe of ſad mourning and heavy lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; in which (according to the warrant of the word, and lau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dable cuſtome of the Church in all ages) he hath beene ſought unto by prayer and faſting:<note place="margin">Deum quaſi manu facta pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>anonibus am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biamus orantes. Tert.</note> with which the Church hath ever plyed the Lord in the day of their diſtreſſe, as it were <hi>beleaguering heaven with the Army of their prayers:</hi> This courſe having beene ſo long by authority continued in this place, I conceive it is too late for me after the revolution of ſo many ſolemne faſts, now to goe about to open to you what is required of Gods People in the day of their ſolemne humiliation and faſting. I am confident that you (who have ſpent ſo many dayes in that Chriſtian duty) have been fully inſtructed there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in from ſundry learned diſcourſes heretofore preſented to you. Neither will I ſtand to pleade before you for the neceſſary conjunction of prayer to your faſting: truſting you have not ſo learned Chriſt, as to divide the duties which he in his word hath coupled together. That which remaines for me (the meaneſt of Gods Labourers) to aime at, for the preſent, I take to be this; (that whereas you have faſted and prayed, and in both continued ſo long) to endeavour now to raiſe up your hearts and quicken your ſpirits in the continuance of this duty of ſeeking God by earneſt prayer: and the rather becauſe aſſuredly the Lord (on whom we waite in theſe holy duties) in the end will be exalted, that be may have compaſſion on them that patiently waite and pray for his mercy: would you be aſſured of it? take his word
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:154626:4"/>that if you waite and be ſtrong in your dependance upon our God, be will at length ariſe for your comfort. So much deſire I to cleare un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you this day: and for that cauſe I humbly pray you with all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence to hearken to what you ſhall finde written for that purpoſe,</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSAL. 31.24.</hi>
               </bibl> Be of good courage, and he ſhall ſtrengthen your heart, all ye that hope in the LORD.</q>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE man, whom God in this life, hath ſingled out by faith to depend upon him, is ſure to meet with troubles of all ſorts, and in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which will not faile to attend upon that dependance: Yet hee, whoſe heart is ingaged in all theſe ſtormes to cleave unto the Lord, muſt ſtill ſue to him for deliverance: which having once ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, hee muſt then with all thankfulneſſe acknowledge it: <hi>For a gratefull acknowledgement of received favours, is the great tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute due to the Lord for all the favours which hee beſtows upon his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple:</hi> Yea, certainely hee who is bleſſed with the favour of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance, and truely, or throughly affected with the free mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy therein, will not onely himſelfe bee thankfull; but ſtudy to draw on others to praiſe the Lord in way of thankfulneſſe for the favours whereof hee taſtes,</p>
            <p>See all this in this Pſalme, <hi>David</hi> dangerouſly purſued by his enemies, ſues to God for deliverance: his Petition, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the ſeverall arguments wherewith hee backes it, are ſet down from the beginning of the Pſalme to the 20. ver. from whence to ver. 24. hee thankfully acknowledges the received mercy vouchſafed to him, and all ſuch as truſt in God: which favour hee amplifies ſundry wayes. Then hee deſires all Gods people to love the Lord. Laſtly, upon all theſe ſeverall bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches hee infers, what is the duty of Gods people in all their troubles; even this, to encourage themſelves in ſtrengthning their hearts, and waiting upon the Lord: this hee layes down in the words of my Text: which may bee termed a comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table direction to ſtrengthen the beleeving ſoule, againſt all heart-breaking, or ſoule-rending feares, or diſtractions what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever:
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:154626:4"/>In which words our Prophet preſcribes the beſt and moſt ſoveraign cordiall that can bee given in ſuch a condition<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> when Gods people are overwhelmed with feares: and I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you when can it bee judged more ſeaſonable to bee diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſed of, then in theſe dayes? wherein for no ſhort ſpace of time (though now and then of late, God hath come unto us with ſweet refreſhing beames of mercy) it hath falne out with moſt men, as of old with <hi>Ahaz,</hi> and his people,<note place="margin">Eſa 7.2.</note> 
               <hi>Whoſe hearts were moved</hi> (with feare) <hi>as the trees of the Foreſt are moved with the wind:</hi> and hath not this been generally our condition a long time? in which, whoſe heart is not ready to bee ſurpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed with feares? unleſſe it bee ſome <hi>ſonne of Belial,</hi> who being beſotted with his luſts, paſſeth his time without feare of God, or his judgements. But to you, to whom the day ſeemeth gloomy, and the light of your comfort hath been long eclip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed;<note place="margin">1 King. 18 44.</note> to whom trouble hath riſen up as the cloud did to <hi>Elijah</hi> his ſervant, which though at the firſt it was but <hi>little like a mans hand;</hi> yet ſpeedily cauſed <hi>it the face of heaven to looke blacke:</hi> ſo hath the cloudy ſtorm of our unnaturall troubles ſpred it ſelf to the darkning of all our comforts.</p>
            <p>Now to ſuch as notwithſtanding all this, yet wait for com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort from the Lord, my Text is a ſure guide to lead them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to comfort: hearken therfore to what the Lord ſpeaks in the ſame, that you may not bee to ſeek for comfort, when heavy ſtorms of troubles ſhall ſwallow up others that feare nothing till it ſeiſe upon them. To you then (whoſe hope in all trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles reſts on the Lord) the Lord ſpeakes in my Text, ſaying, <hi>All you that wait on the Lord, bee ſtrong, and hee ſhall eſtabliſh your heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Wherein ſee, firſt, to whom the Prophet doth addreſſe his ſpeech, to ſuch <hi>as patiently wait upon the Lord:</hi> Secondly, what it is that hee requires of them, to <hi>ſtrengthen themſelves, to waxe ſtrong or bee valiant:</hi> Thirdly, in the laſt place conſider what hee promiſeth to them, that their <hi>hearts ſhall bee raiſed up in ſtrength.</hi> You ſee the parts, the ſumme of all is a leſſon full of comfort to all ſuch as patiently hope in the Lord, and from theſe parts, I ſhall draw forth three propoſitions to inſiſt upon by Gods aſſiſtance and your patience at this time:</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:154626:5"/>
            <p> The firſt is, that <hi>Gods people are taught by the Lord in all their troubles to waite patiently upo him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond is, that <hi>ſuch as waite patiently upon the Lord muſt rouſe up themſelves with ſtrength and courage to wait further upon him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The third followeth, that <hi>when Gods people with courage and patience waite upon him, he will encreaſe their courage.</hi> To theſe three Propoſitions ſhall I limit my ſpeech, onely my deſire is, as they find, ſo they may leave you attentive.</p>
            <p>The firſt of them ariſeth from the firſt conſiderable branch of the words, the perſons to whom they are directed: he di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rects his ſpeech to ſuch as <hi>patiently waite upon the Lord.</hi> The word in the originall here rendered in our language <hi>to waite</hi> ſignifieth,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> to be <hi>carried out after any thing with a wonderfull de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire to enjoy it.</hi> Secondly, to be <hi>ſorry we are ſo long without the fruition</hi> of that we thus deſire. Thirdly, <hi>patiently to waite</hi> for it: all theſe are elegantly hinted in the uſe of the <hi>word</hi> by <hi>Job:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job. 29 21.23.</note> whileſt he ſets forth what was the opinion which once men had of his wiſedome and counſell when he ſpake in the publike before others, he ſayes they <hi>eagerly deſired to heare him,</hi> that appeared in <hi>their ſilence when he ſpake;</hi> they reſted in it as the beſt and choifeſt counſell that could be preſcribed to them: as the raine is welcome to the dry and parched ground, it ſucks it in: ſo was his counſell to ſuch as heard it, and wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for it. Thus the godly here are deſcribed from their wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon God, which implies, Firſt, their deſire after God; Secondly, their griefe, that yet they enjoy not the Lord ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to their deſire; Thirdly, their patient attending up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on God for that which they deſire: and from hence ariſeth our firſt propoſition; that</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gods people are taught by God in all their afflictions, and under all their troubles patiently to waite upon the Lord.</hi> 
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctr. </seg>1</label>
            </p>
            <p>This is their practiſe, and therefore in my text they are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed by that propertie, <hi>They waite upon the Lord;</hi> they are a generation of <hi>waiters,</hi> being carried on with earneſtneſſe of deſires to ſee what God will doe for them in their troubles; they long for the Lord, and yet patiently waite upon him.</p>
            <p>To cleare this truth unto you, firſt, I will prove the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, make it good that it ſhould bee ſo; ſecondly, point forth unto you
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:154626:5"/>the true grounds from whence this waiting in Gods children doth ariſe, which being laid open I doubt not but the truth of the Doctrine with caſe will bee manifeſted to all that heare it.</p>
            <p>As for the firſt, that Gods people muſt waite upon him;<note place="margin">1. God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires it.</note> know firſt that this is the thing which <hi>God requires</hi> of all his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, that in all their afflictions they ſhould waite upon him for his helpe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 55.22. <hi>caſt your burthen upon the Lord,</hi> ſaith the Prophet, <hi>and he ſhall nouriſh thee:</hi> The words in the origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall are ſignificant, and runne thus; <hi>Caſt your carefull burden on the Lord and hee will ſuſtaine thee, q. d.</hi> looke whatſoever it is thou art carefull may bee afforded to thee in all thy wants and neceſſities, caſt thy care for that thing upon the Lord, and waite on him to receive it from his bountifull hands; for hee is ſure to ſuſtaine and nouriſh thee with the ſame. To the ſame purpoſe ſpeakes our bleſſed Saviour, <hi>Luke</hi> 21.19. <hi>By your patience</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>poſſeſſe your ſoules:</hi> that ſpeech followes upon a ſad relation of heavie troubles that were to enſue; hee tells them, <hi>Nation ſhall riſe againſt nation, there ſhall bee great Warres, Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes and perſecutions, the Parents ſhall betray their Children, and one friend another;</hi> and to imbitter all, he addes, <hi>they ſhall bee ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of all men for his ſake;</hi> Now what might his poore unarmed children thinke ſhould become of them in all theſe troubles? might they not conclude, in the eye of reaſon there was no ſafetie for them in ſuch a condition? what ſhall they doe? our bleſſed Saviour anſwers, <hi>poſſeſſe your ſoules in Patience,</hi> as if he had ſaid unto them, although you be compaſſed about with troubles on every hand, yet do you continue waiting quietly upon the Lord, there ſhall not a haire of your heads periſh, therefore wait you upon the Lord. Thus God requires it of his people.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the Lord goes farther and <hi>pronounces them all bleſſed</hi> that doe ſo, <hi>Eſa.</hi> 30.18. <hi>Bleſſed are all they that waite for him:</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. God ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts them bleſſed.</note> their waiting in that place is oppoſed to the prepoſterous courſe followed by them, and mentioned in the beginning of the Chapter: when God threatned to bring an enemy upon them; they following their owne counſells are not long in reſolving what to doe; they'l downe to <hi>Aegypt,</hi> and ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then themſelves in their confederacie with them to boe aided
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:154626:6"/>by their aſſiſtance, and they make haſte to doe this: but there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in they conſulted not with God; therefore hee tells them, the <hi>ſtrength of Pharaoh ſhould bee their ſhame, and their truſt in Aegypt their confuſion, i. e.</hi> not able to profit them: After this hee comes to preſcribe a better and more ſure way of deliverance unto them then that could bring forth, and what is that? He ſets it down in the 15. <hi>Verſe, In reſt and quietneſſe ſhall you be ſaved, in quietneſſe and confidence ſhall bee your ſtrength:</hi> (here was a ſweet and wholeſome counſell, could they have followed it, but that they would not doe) the meaning of it was this, that they ſhould depend upon the Lord and on his ſtrength, but they would not; yet ſome amongſt them did ſo, and hee ſaith, <hi>ſuch are bleſſed;</hi> by which place it appeares that God would have his people waite upon him in their extremities, which if they doe they are ſure to bee bleſſed of him.</p>
            <p>Now then if God require his people in all their troubles to waite upon him, if hee pronounce them bleſſed that doe ſo, then wee may ſurely conclude, that it is their dutie in all their troubles patiently to waite upon the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Hope floweth from Faith.</note>To cleare this truth yet further unto you, in as much as Gods people are here ſtiled <hi>waiters upon the Lord,</hi> conſider in the next place from whence it comes that when they are incloſed with troubles, yet they can reſolve with patience to attend up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lord? firſt their patient waiting upon the Lord is the worke of their <hi>hope,</hi> and that ſprings from their <hi>faith</hi> in God: hee that dare truſt to the goodneſſe of the Lord for the preſent, aſſuredly will waite upon him or expect theſe good things from him for the time to come: no man can poſſibly hope in the Lord, that doth not by faith truſt in the Lord, and ſettles not the affiance of his ſoule upon him: it is <hi>hope</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that raiſeth up the heart with expectation of that which <hi>faith</hi> laies hold on; for <hi>faith</hi> being informed in the <hi>truth</hi> and <hi>faithfulneſſe</hi> of God; reſting alſo ſatisfied that there is no <hi>power</hi> wanting in God to make good his Word, and withall medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating on his <hi>free mercy</hi> doclared in the promiſe; when the heart upon theſe and the <hi>like grounds</hi> is brought to truſt in the Lord, then will it with patience waite, being raiſed up with hope one day to enjoy what it waits for; therefore it is faith
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:154626:6"/>that makes the heart in hope to waite upon the Lord. Hence is it that as God worketh <hi>faith</hi> to beleeve in him, ſo hee alone raiſeth up the heart with <hi>hope</hi> to waite for the accompliſhment of that Word which by faith it hath received;<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſſed bee the Lord,</hi> ſaith <hi>Peter, which according to his abundant mercy hath be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten us againe unto a lively hope, by the reſurrection of Jeſus Chriſt from the dead:</hi> It is the Lord alone that is the author of the <hi>hope</hi> that waites upon him, yea and that by the promiſe received and reſted on by faith;<note place="margin">Col. 1.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3</note> for which cauſe it is called <hi>the hope of the Goſpell,</hi> that is, the things which are laid forth in the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, the expectation whereof raiſeth up the heart; which gave occaſion to that holy man to ſay, <hi>Spes fine fide quomodo eſſe poſſit, non invenio. Nemo enim ſe ſperat poſſe aſſequi, quod eſſe non credit;</hi> all which confirmes that faith bringeth forth hope,<note place="margin">Aug. Sent.</note> and hope makes the ſoule patiently to waite upon the Lord: If any man would know what are the things they waite for; I anſwer they are ſuch as God in his ſacred Word hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to give; for <hi>hope</hi> which raiſeth up the heart to <hi>waite,</hi> is alwayes grounded upon the <hi>Word of promiſe;</hi> therefore <hi>David</hi> coupleth theſe two together; <hi>My ſoule hath waited and I have truſted in his Word,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 130.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Gods Word is the thing that hope flowing from faith doth waite for. Yet further, the good things pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed and waited for are ſuch as are neither <hi>paſt,</hi> nor <hi>preſent;</hi> but good things that are <hi>abſent</hi> and yet to <hi>come</hi> are the things which ſuch as wraite on God doe looke for;<note place="margin">Aug. Enchir. ca. <hi>8.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Spes non niſi bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narum rerum eſt, nec niſi futurarum;</hi> the things hoped for are yet in expectation: I will not ſcan the particulars which hope waiteth for, it is enough in the generall to know that <hi>whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver</hi> good things God hath <hi>promiſed,</hi> and hath not yet <hi>fully per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed</hi> his promiſe therein, hope waits upon him for all theſe things, as whether it bee <hi>deliverance from trouble, improving the worke of grace, affording daily bread, treading downe Satan under our feet, &amp;c.</hi> whatſoever are the good things with which God hath promiſed to bleſſe his people either in this life or that which is to come, <hi>hope</hi> waiteth for the fruition of them all.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Hope it groun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded upon the promiſe.</note>Secondly, whatſoever the troubles of Gods children fall out to be, yet they are raiſed up to waite upon him, becauſe they have Gods Word to reſt themſelves upon, they well know
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:154626:7"/>though heaven and earth ſhould paſſe away, that God is true and will bee faithfull in all that hee hath ſpoken; ſuch a heart will bee brought to waite upon God, which knowes that hee hath ſaid,<note place="margin">Pſal. 89.34.</note> 
               <hi>I will not alter the thing that is gone out of my lips,</hi> that is ſpoken, I confeſſe, of a ſpeciall promiſe unto <hi>David,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning his ſucceſſor in the Crowne, but it holds as true in every promiſe made by God to his people, hee will not alter it nor falſifie his faith, for the <hi>ſure mercies of David</hi> ſpoken of in the Pſalmes, are the priviledges of the Covenant of grace made good to beleevers; the due and ſerious conſideration hereof is the thing which upholds the heart to waite upon the Lord though it hath all the world againſt it, whilſt it ſees Gods promiſe and then lookes out for his <hi>efficiencie</hi> to make good the ſame, ever knowing that hee that ſpeakes the word will in his due time give a being to it.</p>
            <p>There are two things which may hinder a man from mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing good his word or fulfilling of his promiſes, <hi>impotency or careleſneſſe:</hi> when either he is not able, or not carefull to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme what he hath promiſed: but the beleeving heart raiſed up to waite on God, knowes well that neither of theſe can be found in him: His <hi>almighty power</hi> admits not of impotency or weakeneſſe, no thing can let or hinder him <hi>(to whom all things are poſſible)</hi> from doing what he pleaſeth: neither is He care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe of his promiſe, for his <hi>faithfulneſſe</hi> will not admit of that. I might alſo put you in mind of the infiniteneſſe of his <hi>mercy,</hi> whereby hee is drawne to commiſerate and pitie his children in all their troubles; a mother is tender of her children, but the Lord more: for <hi>though ſhe ſhould</hi> prove unnaturall and <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get the fruite of her wombe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 49 15.</note> 
               <hi>yet the Lord will not forget his people,</hi> what made the King of <hi>Ammon</hi> his ſervants waite for mercy at <hi>Ahabs</hi> hands?<note place="margin">1 King. 20.31</note> 
               <hi>They had heard the Kings of Iſrael were mercifull Kings,</hi> thereupon were they encouraged to waite upon him for favour, though they had no promiſe of it; it is an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted truth, where a petitioner knowes there is proneneſſe or a ready inclination in a partie (to whom hee ſues) to ſhow mercy, that will make him waite for helpe from him above all others: Thus Gods people finde in God reaſon enough to waite upon him for the fulfilling of his Word; they know that hee
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:154626:7"/>is a God faithfull in his word, every way able to performe it, and infinitely mercifull towards all that waite upon him for the ſame.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, with patience they waite upon him, becauſe they know that the ſame God who hath made the promiſe to them, hath alſo appointed or ſet out the period of time, in which his promiſe ſhall undoubtedly be fulfilled to them: for though the faithfulneſſe of Gods promiſe is knowne to them, yet the particular period or ſet time, wherein this promiſe ſhall take effect, is unknowne to them; (<hi>for whom it is not to know the times and ſeaſons which the Father bath put in his owne power;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 1.7.</note>) this makes them waite with patience till the happy revolution of the time come about, which God hath ſet out to the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formance of his promiſe. God promiſed faithfull <hi>Abraham that in</hi> Iſaac <hi>his ſeed ſhould be called:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 21.12.</note> yet holy <hi>Iſaac</hi> did not preſently ſee that promiſe performed, for he was marry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (as may bee collected from the Hiſtory) twenty yeers and had no childe: yet hee waited for it; the evidence of his wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting was, <hi>Hee prayed and God heard him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gen. 25.21. Luk. 2.25.</note> 
               <hi>and his wife conceived.</hi> It is ſaid of old <hi>Simeon, Hee waited for the conſolation of Iſrael, i. e.</hi> for the revealing of Chriſt in the fleſh; God having promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to him, <hi>Hee ſhould not ſee death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 26.</note> 
               <hi>till hee had ſeene the Lords Chriſt:</hi> hee knew not when that would bee, yet hee beleeved and waited for it: upon this very ground it is, that God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires waiting in his people, <hi>Habak.</hi> 2.3. <hi>The viſton is for an appointed time, but at laſt it ſhall ſpeak and not lie: though it tarry, waite; for it ſhall ſurely come and not ſtay:</hi> The viſion hee ſpeaks of contained both the deſtruction of the enemy, and comfort of his Church: there was a time determined by the Lord, wherein both theſe ſhould take place, yet though the iſſue were certain, the haſty affections of men thought the time long: now becauſe they knew not when it ſhould bee, God requires of them to waite: therefore the not knowing of the time when Gods promiſe ſhall take place, draws ſuch as beleeve the promiſe to waite upon the Lord.</p>
            <p>Thus have I cleered the firſt propoſition, <hi>That Gods people waite upon him;</hi> I ſhall forbeare the uſe till I have proved the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther two, and then give you a joynt application of them all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:154626:8"/>
            <p> In the next place ſee and conſider what is the thing which hee calls for from theſe waiters: <hi>Bee ſtrong yee that wait upon the Lord;</hi> or <hi>bee confirmed:</hi> that word here rendred, <hi>bee yee ſtrong,</hi> or of good courage,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> doth properly import to waxe ſtrong and prevaile: ſo is it uſed, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 28.20. when <hi>Tilgath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pilneſer,</hi> came to the aſſiſtance of <hi>Ahaz,</hi> it is ſaid, <hi>hee troubled him and did not ſtrengthen him,</hi> or hee grew not ſtronger by his help as hee expected: the word therefore imports a corroboration of that ſtrength which a man hath: ſo the Lord here requires that all ſuch as waite upon him ſhould waxe ſtrong, and take heart by their relying upon him; from whence ariſeth our ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond propoſition, that <hi>ſuch as patiently wait upon God muſt rouſe up themſelves with ſtrength and courage, to wait further upon him.</hi> The heart that hath choſen the Lord for his God, and pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently doth wait upon him, muſt grow to a holy kind of great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and magnanimity, becauſe it is ſet upon the great God. To evidence this truth, I will indevour, firſt, to open the way, how this may bee done, whereby you may ſee wherein this heroicall valour ſtands, by which hee that waits on God is confirmed in his ſtrength: Secondly, that ſuch as wait upon God muſt gather ſtrength and courage to themſelves in their dependance upon him: which being done, then in the third place wee will ſhew the reaſons of it; the opening of all which will ſufficiently cleare the Doctrine: the firſt will lay forth the way how to attain it: The ſecond will manifeſt the ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity of it: and the third ſhall cleare the reaſons of it.</p>
            <p>For the firſt, let us inquire wherein this courage ſtands, that ſo you may the better ſee how a Soule that <hi>waits upon the Lord</hi> may <hi>waxe ſtrong:</hi> A point needfull to bee diſcuſſed, and ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into by every one, who deſires with ſtrength to wait upon the Lord: and the rather, becauſe many ſeem to bee raiſed up with ſtoutneſſe, when indeed their <hi>ſtoutneſſe</hi> is not true cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, but meere raſhneſſe, or inconfiderateneſſe: Neither is the valour or courage mentioned in my Text, that <hi>confident courage</hi> or holy <hi>boldneſſe,</hi> whereby the beleeving ſoule doth reſt on God for ſalvation by faith in <hi>Jeſus Chriſt:</hi> nor is it the <hi>aſſurance of hope</hi> it ſelfe, by which the ſoule waits on God for the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of his promiſe, (indeed the conſidence or cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:154626:8"/>here ſpoken of is required in all ſuch, as beleeve and wait for the promiſe; <hi>Faith and Hope</hi> bring forth this courage, and it is an effect of hope rather than hope it ſelfe.) But in a word, this courage is that confidence: which is wrought in man by the power of faith and ſtrength of hope in God; which maketh him goe on cheerfully in <hi>the particular worke</hi> to which God hath called him; it is eſpecially diſcovered in theſe things:</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, When a man is undaunted, ſtout, and reſolute, to do the ſpeciall thing which God requireth of him:<note place="margin">This courage is ſeene. Act. 4.</note> therefore, that which here is phraſed <hi>waxing ſtrong,</hi> elſewhere is called <hi>boldneſſe:</hi> as <hi>Peter</hi> being examined before the <hi>Rulers, Elders, Scribes,</hi> and <hi>High-prieſts,</hi> by whoſe authority hee had done that miracle, hee doth freely and cleerly confeſſe it to bee done in the name, and by the power of Jeſus Chriſt: this free confeſſion of the truth, there is called <hi>boldneſſe,</hi> and why?<note place="margin">Verſ. 13.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee waxed ſtrong and would not ſhrink a whit from that, to which hee was called: this was the very thing which they craved of God by prayer, ſaying, <hi>Grant unto thy ſervants to ſpeak thy word with boldneſſe.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 4.29.</note> You ſee then what is meant by <hi>waxing ſtrong:</hi> even this, to raiſe up the ſpirit to a holy bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to doe that, which God cals a man to do: It is not cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, but preſumption, for a man to adventure upon that work to which hee is not called of God; and though hee bee reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute in purſuance of it, yet his reſolute adventure is not the boldneſſe that comes from faith or hope: a man his holy bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe muſt bee ſeen in doing that, to which hee is called. <hi>Peter</hi> ſayes, <hi>Let them that ſuffer according to the will of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 4.19.</note> 
               <hi>commit their ſoules to him in wel-doing, as to a faithfull Creator:</hi> Where hee would have Gods children to arme themſelves with courage againſt all troubles and tentations that may befall them: but how ſhall they doe this? they muſt ſo order things, that if they doe ſuffer, they may ſuffer according to Gods will, which they ſhall doe, if they ſuffer in doing that which God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands them to doe: God commands <hi>Jeremiah</hi> that hee goe forth with courage to ſpeak to the people, O but how ſhall hee attain to this courage? hee muſt do what <hi>God commands him,</hi> and ſpeake what the Lord <hi>will have him</hi> to ſpeake,<note place="margin">Jer. 1.7, 8.</note> then hee
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:154626:9"/>needes not bee afraid of their faces.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, as this holy courage in a man ariſing from faith and hope ever ey's the worke, to which he was called of God; ſo it makes him adventure upon that worke not in the confidence of his owne ſtrength, but to reſt on God for <hi>his ſtrength</hi> to inable him to goe through the worke. <hi>David</hi> was exceeding ſtout when he durſt engage himſelfe to grapple with that Gyant <hi>Goliah:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 17.45.</note> yet he did it not in confidence of his own ſtrength, but of the Lord, which he dare proclaime to the ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror of the Gyant at their firſt meeting: that learned <hi>Apoſtle</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> would have his Epheſians <hi>ſtrong in the Lord,</hi> and the <hi>power of his might:</hi> he would have them to ſtrengthen themſelves in fulfilling Gods will, but he would have them alſo to reſt aſſured that that muſt be attained to by the power of <hi>God,</hi> without which no man can in a holy way fulfill the will of God.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, when a holy diſpoſition is thus farre raiſed up with a valorous reſolution as to put his hand to Gods worke, in conſidence of Gods aſſiſtance; then doth it make a man tread under his feete all difficulties which may ſtand in his way to keepe him off from ſulfilling of Gods will: let <hi>Paul</hi> his practice witneſſe it: he reſolves <hi>to ſtay at Epheſus untill Pentecoſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 16.8.9.</note> 
               <hi>and why? a great doore and effectuall was opened to him; and there were many adverſaries:</hi> he had a faire opportunity to preach the Goſpel: (upon which crrand he was ſent of God) O but he had many adverſaries to reſiſt him, there were many difficulties for him to overcome: yet you ſee by his words, he gives no place to feares on that occaſion, ſtay he will, and there with courage waite on God in ſulfilling of his miniſtery to which he was called of God. It is ſaid, <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 11.4. <hi>He that obſerveth the winde ſhall not ſow, and he that regardeth the clouds ſhall not reape: Solomon</hi> is there perſwading men to be large<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearted, and open-handed to the poore: O but when an unbelieving heart is lock't up in a covetous breaſt, nature is wonderfully apt to deviſe many excuſes to keepe him off from ſhewing his benevolence to the poore: <hi>he will tell you, he knows not but his lot may fall to be in want himſelfe; he may grow old, when nature is enſeebled with age and cannot attend his calling: and bath
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:154626:9"/>be not then neede to lay up ſomething againſt that evill time? he may be overtaken with ſickneſſe, which may not onely keepe him from labour, but make him ſpend all he got before,</hi> &amp;c. theſe and a thouſand ſuch frivolous excuſes can corrupt nature frame, to hinder a man from cheere ulneſſe in relieving them that want: in <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> his anſwer to all theſe doubts, he reaſons from the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdity that followes upon ſuch baſe and vaine excuſes: this is all one, ſaith the <hi>Wiſeman,</hi> as if an husband-man ſhould hold off from ſowing his ground, fearing leſt the winde ſhould blow hard and trouble him in ſcattering of his ſeede, (when yet there is no great gale of winde ſtirring) yet he puts off his worke from day to day onely upon that ſurmiſed feare: or as if another ſhould ſeare to thruſt in his ſickle to reape downe his corne, becauſe he ſees the Firmament to be cloudy, which makes him feare raine; if any man upon theſe or the like feares ſhould forbeare to doe that which his calling requires and war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rants him to doe, he would certainely be cryed downe for a foole by all wiſemen: So here when God calls a man to any worke, he muſt not forbeare or keepe off from doing that which God calls him to, upon feare of what troubles may en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſue; but rouſe up his ſpirit and ſtrive to fulfill his worke: therein will appeare his courage, in breaking through all dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties whatſoever to honour God in obedience to his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand.</p>
            <p>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, this holy courage goes yet farther in managing any warrantable undertaking for God, when hee hath ſeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly weighed with himſelfe Gods call to the worke, when hee conſiders hee did not ruſh upon it in the confidence of his owne ſtrength, then <hi>comes hee with quietneſſe to carry, on the worke and leaves the ſucceſſe to the Lord.</hi> The three children did reſt aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that it was Gods will they ſhould not defile themſelves with that idolatrous worſhip, they knew that God at his pleaſure could deliver them; therefore doe they waite upon him with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any diſtiuſt at all, ſaying, <hi>Our God whom wee ſerve is able to deliver us from the fiery Furnace, and hee will deliver us out of thy hand.</hi> there was their hope; now followes their courage, <hi>but if hee will not, BE IT KNOWNE to thee O King we will not ſerve thy Gods, nor worſhip the golden image that thou haſt ſet up;</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:154626:10"/>they were not troubled about the <hi>ſucceſſe,</hi> but left that wholly to the Lord, and did what God required of them; ſo did ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>David</hi> when hee was to encounter with <hi>Goliah,</hi> the ſtorie is knowne to you; So when <hi>Paul</hi> was commanded to paſſe into <hi>Arabia,</hi> and there preach the Goſpell, where hee had ſmall hope of ſucceſſe in his miniſterie; <hi>hee conſulted not with fleſh and blood, but immediatly went on to preach the Goſpel,</hi> and left the <hi>ſucceſſe</hi> to the Lord that called him.<note place="margin">Gal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Thus have you heard wherein this holy ſtrength of courage is mainely to bee ſeene: now if you ſhall goe further, you may with eaſe in the ſecond place ſee the neceſſitie of theſe ſeverall ſteps of this ſpirituall courage in any undertaking for the Lord; and that ſhall be made manifeſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you in foure things.</p>
            <p>The firſt whereof is this, as God requires of his people to waite upon him,<note place="margin">1. God requires courage in his people.</note> ſo likewiſe <hi>he requires</hi> that they ſhould gather ſtrength to corroborate or confirme themſelves in their waiting upon him; beſides our Text, wherein hee calls upon ſuch as waite upon God <hi>to ſtrengthen themſelves;</hi> conſider what hee ſpeakes to this purpoſe elſewhere:<note place="margin">Zeph. 3.16.17.</note> hee ſaith, <hi>Feare thou not O Zion, let not thine heart bee ſaint; the Lord thy God in the midſt of thee is mightie, hee will ſave, hee will rejoyce over thee with joy, hee will quiet himſelfe in his love, hee will rejoyce over thee with joy;</hi> there the Lord it ſetting downe a notable comfort to the reſidue of his afflicted people, and conſider what hee ſaith unto them: <hi>feare not thou O Zion, let not thine heart bee faint;</hi> hee requires of them that they bee ſtout-hearted and couragious: then he ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joynes the reaſon of it, <hi>the Lord thy God in the midſt of thee is mightie, he will ſave, hee will rejoyce over thee with joy, hee will quiet himſelfe in his love, &amp;c.</hi> the reaſon why they ſhould grow in a holy valour, and not bee faint-hearted is, becauſe <hi>God is amongſt them,</hi> and will know them; yea hee delights to ſhew his love and great affection towards them: therefore ſeeing God dwels among his people, and delights to doe them good, hee char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges them that they bee not faint-hearted, but couragious. To this very purpoſe ſpeaketh <hi>Peter</hi> ſaying, <hi>Feare not their feares, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bee troubled,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 3.14.</note> 
               <hi>but ſanctifie the Lord in your hearts:</hi> hee is there ſetting downe the right way how to goe through all afflictions wee meete with in this world, and teacheth the Church how
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:154626:10"/>to beare them ſo as wee may bee bleſſed in the end: If we would doe ſo; firſt, wee muſt lay aſide falſe feares, ſuch as men ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narily are troubled withall, <hi>Let not,</hi> ſaith the bleſſed Apoſtle, <hi>your hearts bee troubled with their feares:</hi> for they become not you that wait upon God. Secondly, the heart with confidence muſt bee raiſed up to waite on God; by this confidence God is ſanctified, and that feare removed; by which place it may appeare, that feare is to bee ſhaken off, and confidence in God is <hi>the way</hi> to doe it, therefore the Lord requires that his people ſhould bee raiſed up in courage and not fearefull whileſt they waite upon him.</p>
            <p>Secondly, as God requires it, ſo when men grow ſtrong in waiting upon him,<note place="margin">2. God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mends courage in his people.</note> the Lord doth highly commend it: how are thoſe <hi>worthies</hi> renowned for their confident waiting upon the Lord? <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.33, 34, 35, <hi>&amp;c. they waxed valiant, of weake were made ſtrong, &amp;c.</hi> therefore are their names honored to this day by the Lord: did not their waiting on God ſo raiſe their ſpirits that they became valiant? was not <hi>Sampſon</hi> ſo valiant by his waiting on God, <hi>that with the jaw-bone of an Aſſe be ſlew a thouſand Philiſtims?</hi> did not <hi>David</hi> by his waiting on God ſlay <hi>Goliah</hi> with a ſtone out of his ſling? and how are both of them ennobled by their valour unto this day?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3. God is angry where courage is wanting.</note>Thirdly, where God finds that ſuch as waite on him wax not ſtout-hearted, or are not filled with courage, <hi>hee checks that want of valour in them;</hi> whilſt they are not filled with courage for the worke about which hee ſends: ſee it in Gods dealing with <hi>Moſes Num.</hi> 20.8. <hi>hee is commanded to ſpeake to the rocke,</hi> and the Lord <hi>tells him, it ſhall give him water;</hi> nevertheleſſe hee ſmote the rocke and ſpake unto the people, but hee is not ſaid to ſpeake to the rocke as hee was commanded; it ſeemes hee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved not that his ſpeaking to the rocke could bring forth water out of it: therefore the Lord tells him, <hi>hee ſhould not bring that Congregation into Canaan:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Num. 20.12.</note> in a word God was angry with him, that hee waxed not ſtrong in waiting upon the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">4. Gods people have been full of courage.</note>Fourthly, the holy practiſe of Gods people recorded in the Scriptures holds forth the ſame truth unto us, in which hee that runnes may reade, that <hi>by their waiting upon God they grew
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:154626:11"/>exceeding ſtrong;</hi> How valiant waxed the three children be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Nebuchadnezzar?</hi> and whence came it? was it not from their <hi>waiting upon God?</hi> they dare tell him, <hi>wee are not carefull to anſwer thee in this matter:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan 6.16, 17.</note> and why? <hi>our God whom wee ſerve is able to deliver us from the fiery Furnace;</hi> you heare of their courage which could not bee allayed by all the threatnings breathed out by that potent King; their patient waiting on the Lord was a ſtrong preſervative againſt them all. <hi>Jeboſaphat</hi> his ſtout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the ſtrength of his courage was teſtified in his ſpeech to his ſubjects,<note place="margin">2 Chron 20.20.</note> ſaying, <hi>Heare mee O Judah, and yee inhabitants of Jeruſalem, put your truſt in the Lord your God, and yee ſhall bee aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red; beleeve yee his Prophets; and yee ſhall proſper:</hi> God had given them by a Prophet a ſpeciall promiſe of victory, and you ſee how valiant that pious Prince waxed upon the receit of it, and how hee laboured to draw others to depend upon the ſame. To the ſame purpoſe ſpeaketh <hi>Hezekiah,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 32.6, 7, 8. <hi>Hee ſpeakes comfortably to them,</hi> ſaith the Text, and it well appeares by the many phraſes he there uſeth to raiſe up their drooping hearts, <hi>hee forbids them to feare,</hi> hee doubles it againe, <hi>and would not have them afraid,</hi> and all upon this ground, becauſe they wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted upon the Lord who was ſtronger then all that could come forth againſt them; the enemies, what had they to aſſiſt them? <hi>an arme of fleſh;</hi> that is, ſuch power as man could afford, but <hi>with them was the Lord their God to helpe them.</hi> I might alſo tell you of the worth of <hi>Nehemiah</hi> his valour,<note place="margin">Nehem. 6.7, 8.</note> who gave no place to the policies and ſubtle craft of the enemies ſeeking to <hi>weaken his hands from the worke;</hi> but with undaunted courage pleaded the falſehood of their accuſations: and would you know from whence it came? even <hi>from his waiting upon God,</hi> which imbold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned him with great courage:<note place="margin">Nehem, 6.9.</note> hee can goe to God and ſay, <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage thou mee,</hi> or ſtrengthen thou my hand. Here likewiſe I might adde the example of <hi>David,</hi> and others, all which I now forbeare, having cleered to you that <hi>ſuch as wait upon God ſhould be filled with courage,</hi> ſeeing God requires it; where hee finds it, hee commends it; hee blames the want of it in his people: Laſtly, this is that whereunto by his <hi>Spirit</hi> hee guides all ſuch as wait upon him.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, let mee intreat you to go one ſtep further with
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:154626:11"/>mee, and dive into the reaſons of the point thus cleared to you;<note place="margin">The reaſon of it.</note> aſſuredly there is great reaſon for it, ſhould not ſuch as waite on God bee ſtrengthned in their hearts, even for this cauſe, <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> becauſe they <hi>have the Lord</hi> to ſettle their truſt upon? Such as patiently waite on God, have God for their God, and are in Covenant with him: that makes them grow to bee magnani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous, or to a holy kind of greatnes wel beſeeming ſuch as wait upon the Lord; the Pſalmiſt ſaith, <hi>Commit thy way to God, truſt in him, hee ſhall bring it to paſſe:</hi> you ſee to whom hee ſpeakes,<note place="margin">Pſal. 37.5.</note> even to them that <hi>truſt in God;</hi> and you ſee likewiſe what hee deſires them to doe, to commit or put over all their care to the Lord, which they cannot doe if they be not raiſed up with cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage, &amp; the ground of that courage is, <hi>they truſt in God;</hi> let them know <hi>Hee</hi> can bring their wayes to paſſe though <hi>they</hi> ſee not how; this was the onely ground of the courage in thoſe three children, mentioned before, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3 <hi>Our God whom we ſerve is able to deliver us:</hi> it was not the power of that enraged Prince, nor the dreadfull heate of his fiery Furnace, that could quench or allay their courage, whoſe confidence was ſetled <hi>on God! Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtome</hi> expounding thoſe words of the Pſalme, <hi>Great is the Lord and worthy to bee praiſed; his greatneſſe is incomprehenſible:</hi> ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth thus: becauſe <hi>thou haſt the great</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>God to rely upon, bee thou alſo of a high courage:</hi> whereby hee would perſwade men to a holy kind of greatneſſe in their courage, becauſe they are grounded upon the great God: hee would not have ſuch to bee of a proud or haughtie diſpoſition, as a frerward hee expounds himſelfe, but as <hi>David</hi> chargeth <hi>Solomon, to bee ſtrong without dread,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Chron. 22.23.</note> 
               <hi>and not diſmaid:</hi> ſuch an heroicall diſpoſition ſhould be in all that pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe their hearts are raiſed up in waiting upon the <hi>great God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, ſuch grow couragious,<note place="margin">2 Gods Spirit fills them with courage Act. 6.10.</note> becauſe <hi>Gods Spirit ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thens</hi> all ſuch as waite upon the Lord: that bleſſed Martyr <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> waxed ſtout in reſiſting his adverſaries, but whence came it? was it not <hi>from the wiſedome and Spirit by which hee ſpake?</hi> that ſtrengthned him that <hi>they were not able to reſiſt him:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 4.</note> So <hi>Peter</hi> ſpake freely to the <hi>Rulers, Elders, and Scribes, and reproved them:</hi> but hee was <hi>then full of the holy Ghoſt, v.</hi> 8. which freedome, <hi>v.</hi> 13. is
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:154626:12"/>called boldneſſe in him: it is the ſame ſpirit which cleares up the truth to their underſtandings, that makes their hearts bold in defence of the truth: it is therefore the powerfull working of Gods Spirit that corroborates their hearts with holy boldneſſe, and makes them <hi>ſet their faces like a flint, Eſa.</hi> 50.7. <hi>and make their foreheads as the Adamant, Ezek.</hi> 3.9. then are they <hi>Lion-like hearted,</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17.10.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">3. God by the promiſe works courage in them.</note>Thirdly, this courage in Gods people ariſeth from the ſtrength which they ſucke from <hi>Gods promiſes;</hi> for <hi>faith and hope</hi> which teacheth them to waite on God conſiders not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly that God gives his <hi>promiſes</hi> to them that lay hold on them by faith, but ſuch a one goes further, and verily beleeves, that God will convey that ſtrength of grace into his heart, which is ſet downe in the promiſe: this, this is that which makes them full of courage in waiting upon the Lord: for it is not with the promiſes of the Goſpell as it is with the Gommande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Law, which are diſtinct from the promiſes; the things commanded to bee done by the Law are not promiſed in the Law; there God requires obedience, but power to yeeld it is not promiſed in the commandement which requires it; but in the Goſpell it is otherwiſe, where that which is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded is alſo promiſed: therefore as faith with one hand laies hold on the Evangelicall commands (which binds the ſoule in all extremitie to waite on God:) ſo with the other hand it laies hold on the promiſe to receive the vertue, ſtrength and power, whereby it may by the promiſe bee brought to waite upon the Lord: this makes it full of courage to waite upon him, having taken hold upon the promiſes by which God conveighs grace into the heart to ſtand in ſuch extre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities: that makes it valiant in waiting upon God, upon whoſe ſtrength it waits in the promiſe.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doct. </seg>3</label> Now to the laſt propoſition conſiderable in the gracious promiſe made to ſuch as with undaunted valour waite upon the Lord: <hi>Hee,</hi> ſaith my Text, <hi>ſhall fortifie or ſtrengthen your hearts:</hi> there is ſome varietie in reading of the words, ſome reade them thus,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Let your hearts be comforted,</hi> or <hi>ſtrengthned:</hi> other, <hi>Hee will ſtrengthen your hearts:</hi> So doth our laſt tranſlation, and as I conceive, this ſenſe will beſt agree to the words, for if we reade
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:154626:12"/>them in the firſt ſenſe, <hi>Let your hearts bee ſtrengthned,</hi> then were they onely a bare repetition of the former words in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther phraſe, as if hee ſaid, <hi>Bee valorous, let your heart hee ſtrengthned you that waite upon the Lord:</hi> but I rather reade them with our tranſlation, <hi>bee valorous and hee will fortifie or ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then your hearts:</hi> who is it that ſhould ſtrengthen them, but the Lord upon whom they waite? <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifieth to fortifie or raiſe up any thing in its ſtrength, which implies, that God will raiſe up the troubled heart in its ſtrength; whence wee gather,<note place="margin">God increaſeth courage in them that have it.</note> 
               <hi>that when Gods people with courage and patience waite upon him in their troubles, he will increaſe their courage:</hi> the Lord by his Prophet promiſeth to adde courage to their courage, and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low ſuch with farther degrees of valour, <hi>bee yee ſtout and he will ſtrengthen your hearts,</hi> ſaith my Text: I will but name this truth, know therefore that is true in a Chriſtians courage, which is ſeene in all other graces; the ready way to have them to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe and <hi>multiply,</hi> is faithfully to <hi>employ</hi> them: for grace when it is well imployed and wiſely husbanded, ever thrives and proſpers; God ever adding new meaſures or degrees to ſuch as faithfully lay out what they have received. This is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently ſet forth to us in the parable of the Talents:<note place="margin">Matth. 25.21.</note> hee that improved his five talents to the gaining of five more receives this anſwer, <hi>Well done good ſervant and faithfull, thou haſt beene faithfull in little, I will make thee ruler over much;</hi> ſo to him that gained two, the ſame anſwer is made; you ſee thereby that their faithfull husbanding and improving what they had, made way for them to receive more from God: ſuch a joyfull <hi>Audite</hi> had theſe faithfull Stewards when they came to give up their accounts; ſo here, the more valorous they were for God, the Lord promiſes to ſtrengthen them by a new additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of courage to what they had,<note place="margin">Eſa. 40.31.</note> 
               <hi>Eſay</hi> tels them, <hi>they that waite upon the Lord ſhall renew their ſtrength, they ſhall lift up their wings as the Eagle, they ſhall run and not bee wearie, they ſhall walke and not faint:</hi> a ſweet and comfortable promiſe wherein the Lord binds himſelfe by his Word, that changes not, to afford new meaſures of ſtrength to ſuch as uſe their ſtrength in walking in his wayes, that they may goe on and advance more cheere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:154626:13"/>in the ſame: ſuch as gather ſtrength to waite upon him ſhall bee enabled at length to flie as the <hi>Eagle</hi> flieth, which of all fowles ſoareth higheſt in her flight; thus will God ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then them more and more; even when to their owne appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion they wax weary and faint.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Grace imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed proſpers.</note>If any man deſires to know the reaſon of it, why ſtrength is added to the ſtrong, and courage well imployed is ſeconded with a freſh ſupply? Let him know as (as I ſaid) this is Gods dealing with men in all their graces which hee beſtowes upon them: a continuall ſupply of grace is afforded to them that faithfully lay out for the Lord what they have received. It is ſaid of our bleſſed Saviour <hi>bee was filled with wiſedome,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luck. 2.40.51.</note> yet fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowes afterwards, <hi>he increaſed in wiſedome;</hi> the ſpirit was ſtrong in Chriſt, and ſtill hee put forth wiſedome bey ond the condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his yeers; the more hee put it forth, the more hee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed in it;<note place="margin">Act. 9.20.22.</note> ſo when <hi>Paul</hi> was called to the miniſtery of the Goſpell, it is ſaid of him, <hi>hee ſtraightwayes preached Chriſt in their Synagogues:</hi> then followes, <hi>hee encreaſed more in ſtrength:</hi> his ſtrength and courage in his worke was ſeconded with freſh ſupplies from God, who abundantly addes to ſuch as improve grace. This I take to bee one maine ground why my Text tells us, hee will fortifie ſuch as are ſtrong in waiting on the Lord: but I ceaſe further to enlarge the proofe of a written truth, and hearken with your patience, to wind up all that I have ſaid in a ſhort application; which I will endeavour to doe by way of teproofe, exhortation, and comfort; and all this, firſt in generall to all the Church; ſecondly, more parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly to this honorable Auditory here preſent.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place, <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>1</label> the propoſitions now obſerved ſpeake to the juſt reprooſe of many: there are three ſorts of people to bee reproved by the firſt of them: If it bee one propertie of Gods people to waite on the Lord in all their troubles, then ſuch as are ſo farre from waiting on God in the day of their troubles that they dare murmure, fret and rage againſt the Lord; ſecondly, ſuch as in their troubles waite not upon God for deliverance, but make uſe of unlawfull meanes to worke their freedome from the ſame; thirdly, ſuch as ſeeme to waite upon God, yet they waite more upon the meanes then
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:154626:13"/>upon the Lord: theſe and many others likewiſe may juſtly bee reproved by the truth before obſerved, and all of them caſt out from having any place among them that patiently waite up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lord. Time gives mee no more freedome but to name theſe; the firſt are ſo farre from teſtifying their dependance in a patient waiting upon the Lord in their troubles, that they are ready with that impious King, who in the extremitie of famine with a heart enraged againſt the Lord uttered that wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full deſperate ſpeech, <hi>Behold, this evill commeth of the Lord,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 King 6.33.</note> 
               <hi>ſhould I attend on the Lord any longer?</hi> Thus many, when they finde not preſent remedy againſt their troubles fall into diſcontented rage, and will waite no longer upon God: the <hi>Iſraelites</hi> often in the extremitie of their dangers and wants fell ſoule upon the Lord, and Gods hand found out to their confuſion ſuch enraged diſpoſitions: to all ſuch I may fafely ſay, they never learned by faith to eye the Lord, nor with patience to waite for deliverance from the Lord. As for ſuch as by unlawfull meanes ſeeke deliverance,<note place="margin">2 King. 1.</note> who with <hi>Amaziah can betake them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves to the God of Ekron; as if there were no God in Iſrael to be wai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedon;</hi> who in their extremities ſticke not by unlawfull meanes and unwarrantable practiſes to ſeeke deliverance from their preſent troubles, ſome with <hi>Saul</hi> can ſeeke to the Witch of Endor, others betraying a good cauſe can deſert the truth and ſubmit to error, thereby to ſpare their lives and eſtates; to them I onely ſay what Jeſus Chriſt hath ſaid, <hi>Luk.</hi> 9.24. <hi>Whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever will ſave his life ſhall loſe it, and whoſoever ſhall loſe his life for my ſake ſhall ſave it:</hi> hee that turnes his backe upon Gods cauſe to avoyd preſent danger to his life or eſtate, ſhall bee a loſer, and no gainer in the end: for what can bee ſaved by that man, who to prevent a temporall loſſe will hazard an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall? aſſuredly ſuch ſavers prove miſerable loſers. To the third ſort, I meane ſuch as ſeeme to waite upon God, and yet they ſtay more upon the <hi>meanes</hi> then upon the <hi>Lord;</hi> ſuch muſt know they are diſorderly in their waiting, they will not wholly forſake the Lord, but adde other things with the Lord, much like to thoſe; <hi>Some truſt in Chariots, ſome in Horſes;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 20.7.</note> but the true waiter upon God will reſolve with <hi>David, to remember the name of the Lord.</hi> Onely I confeſſe there is a lawfull uſe of meanes
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:154626:14"/>which a Chriſtian may uſe, but hee muſt not ſettle the ground of his hopes on the meanes: it is not the uſe of them which is condemned by God in Scriptures, but the relying on them, or waiting principally for help by them, that God condemnes: all theſe are juſtly reproved by our firſt propoſition; as having no right to bee ranked under that character of Gods people, that they <hi>wait upon the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, if all that wait upon God muſt raiſe up their ſpirits, and ſtrengthen themſelves with undaunted courage to wait further upon the Lord; this truth likewiſe reproveth all ſuch as ſeem'd to wait upon the Lord, yet grow not in their courage, but giving way to inordinate feares, quench the ſame: of which ſort are, firſt, ſuch as wanting courage <hi>dare not adventure</hi> upon the work, to which God calls them; Secondly, ſuch as peradventure have ſet upon the work, yet afterwards they are beaten off from proſecuting of it by the <hi>diſcouragements they meet with, in following of the ſame:</hi> Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, ſuch as wholly <hi>deſpaire of the ſucceſſe of their undertakings,</hi> though they have adventured to ingage themſelves in the work, by a warrantable call from God: All theſe ſin againſt the duty mentioned in our ſecond propoſition, and fall ſhort of that heroicall diſpoſition, whereunto all that wait on God ought to aſpire. To the firſt of them I ſay; why ſhould not ſuch remember, that <hi>Gods calling</hi> of them to his work, ſhould bee <hi>enough</hi> to put courage in them to raiſe up their ſpirits to the effecting of it? <hi>Abſolon</hi> ſpeaketh thus to <hi>his</hi> ſervants, <hi>When Amnons heart is merry with Wine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 13.28.</note> 
               <hi>and when I ſay unto you, Smite Amnon, kill him, feare not, have not I commanded you? bee bold therefore and play the men:</hi> the ſervice wherein <hi>hee</hi> imployes them was <hi>deſperate:</hi> for was it not a high attempt to adventure to murder the King's firſt borne Sonne: this was the ſervice hee puts them on; and the argument by which hee would raiſe up their ſpirits to the performance of it, is drawn from his au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, <hi>have not I commanded you?</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>bee bold and play the men:</hi> Could the command of a <hi>mortall man</hi> infuſe that cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and valour into the hearts of <hi>his</hi> ſervants as to make them adventure upon that <hi>deſperate</hi> deſigne? and ſhall not the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the <hi>Almighty God</hi> raiſe up the hearts of <hi>his</hi> people, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:154626:14"/>by him in any work to which <hi>bee</hi> calls them, raiſe up their hearts in following of his command? and the rather, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe never did any man finally miſcarry in executing what God commands: what if they meet with unexpected troubles in purſuing of that which God commands, what then? is not the Lord (upon whom they wait) with them? they have his preſence to goe along with them, and his gracious promiſe of protection of them; yea if they ſhould ſuffer any thing in fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing of his commands, let them know that it is for their honour: did not the holy Apoſtles rejoyce when they were beaten, that <hi>they were accounted worthy to ſuffer any thing for Chriſts ſake?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the ſecond ſort, ſuch as are diſcouraged from the work by ſome croſſe oppoſition they meet with in managing of it: let ſuch remember, though Gods command frees not a man from troubles, whilſt hee doth that which God commands to bee done; yet his command may aſſure him, hee ſhall bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, if hee proſecute the command according to his will: it is true, the Diſciples ſhipt not themſelves into the boat un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till Chriſt commanded them to prepare a boat for their paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage: and it is alſo true, that in their paſſage they met with foule weather at ſea, whereby they were in danger of ſuffering ſhipwrack; but what of all this? did not the Lord ariſe for their comfort, ſtill the ſtormy tempeſt, and gave them ſafe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverance? Gods children in all the tempeſtuous ſtormes they meet with in fulfilling Gods commands, had recourſe for comfort to the Lord, even upon this ground, becauſe God ſent them on the errand wherein they meet with trouble: <hi>Amos</hi> was croſt in his Miniſtery, and complained of by that wicked Prieſt unto the King; hee was in a great ſtrait, yet he beares up his courage upon the Lords command, See it <hi>Amos</hi> 7.14, 15 God is with all them that execute what hee commands: Such may well ſay as <hi>Elijah</hi> to his ſervant, <hi>Feare not; there are more with us than bee with them that are againſt us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the laſt ſort, I meane ſuch as <hi>deſpaire</hi> of the ſucceſſe of buſineſſe undertaken by the warrand of Gods Word: thoughts of that nature muſt not abate their courage, nor hinder their valour from proſecuting that whereunto they are called; but
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:154626:15"/>muſt remember it is their dutie to fulfill what <hi>they are called to,</hi> and leave the <hi>ſucceſſe to the Lord;</hi> ſo did the three Children as we heard. It is a maine ſleight of Satan to draw a man to vex and torment himſelfe about the ſucceſſe of his juſt underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings; and therein hee doth diſable a man from going on with courage: all theſe juſtly from hence to bee reproved.</p>
            <p>The third propoſition reproves them that labour not to <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove</hi> the graces they have received, not conſidering how with the unfaithfull ſervant lapping up his Talent in a Napkin, they not onely prevent themſelves of receiving more, but make way to bee ſtript of all they have: I can but onely name theſe things unto you.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>2</label> Our ſecond uſe is for exhortation: &amp; here will I joyne the firſt and ſecond propoſition together; that is, bee <hi>exhorted to bee va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lourous for the Lord, that you may bee bleſſed of the Lord with a fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther degree of ſpirituall and undaunted courage in managing of Gods work. And to the end you may grow valourous for the Lord, I deſire every man to conſider:</hi> Firſt, his <hi>owne weakeneſſe</hi> and inſufficiency to any worke that is pleaſing to the Lord; aſſuredly hee that goeth on in the confidence of his owne ſtrength, when hee comes to bee oppoſed, hee ſhall by wofull experience finde his valour to faile him, and his courage to bee gone; who was more ſtrengthned in his courage to proſecute the cauſe of God then that holy Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> was? or who could adventure more to advance it then hee did? and would you know from whence did his courage ariſe; take it in his owne words, <hi>not,</hi> ſaith hee,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 3.5.</note> 
               <hi>that wee are ſufficient of our ſelves to think any thing as of our ſelves, but our ſufficiency is of God:</hi> there was the firſt ſtep from whence hee aſcended to that valour: the due and ſerious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of his owne inſufficiency made him ſticke cloſe to the Lord for helpe. Secondly, let a man weigh with himſelfe that <hi>God hath called him to the worke,</hi> thereby ſhall his heart bee fortified alſo: thus did <hi>David</hi> encourage <hi>Solomon,</hi> ſaying, <hi>The Lord hath choſen thee to build the houſe of the Sanctuary,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Chron. 28.10.</note> 
               <hi>bee ſtrong therefore and doe it.</hi> Thirdly, let ſuch conſider that God <hi>will ever bee</hi> with ſuch as hee calls to any work: you know how the Prieſts were to animate the people when they were to goe forth to warre againſt their enemies: they were thus to ſpeake unto
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:154626:15"/>them; <hi>You are come this day unto battell againſt your enemies, let not your hearts faint, neither feare, nor bee amazed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 20.1, 3, 4.</note> 
               <hi>nor adread of them.</hi> O but the people might have replyed, their Horſes and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riots are in our eyes, our adverſaries goe beyond us in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber: yet for all this they muſt not bee dejected with feare, and why? <hi>For the Lord your God goeth with you:</hi> the conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Gods preſence going along with them, whom hee hath called to any hard undertaking, muſt raiſe up their hearts to carry on that work. Fourthly, ſuppoſe that ſuch meet with dyſaſters in following of Gods work: yet if they would bee fortifyed againſt them, behold God hath promiſed that all things ſhall work together for the beſt unto them that love him; Therefore, if thou beeſt croſt in proſecuting of Gods worke for the preſent, yet that hinderance ſhall be as a vantage-ground to take thy riſe to advance it further hereafter. Laſtly, conſider there is an ample reward laid up for all them, <hi>who are ſtedfaſt, unmoveable,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.58.</note> 
               <hi>and abundant alwayes in the worke of the Lord: their labour ſhall not bee in vain in the Lord.</hi> Now by all theſe motives bee exhorted to ſtirre up the grace that is given unto you: that will make you faithfull to God in laying out what you have received, approving your ſelves to him in your ſtewardſhip: that will make you uſefull to the Church of God where you live: and that will open a way of comfort un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you, when you ſhall come to give up the accounts of your ſtewardſhip in the great day of the Lord.</p>
            <p>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe </seg>3</label> My laſt uſe ſhould have been a word of comfort, with which I deſired to have diſmiſſed you: and in it I would have ſpoken to ſuch <hi>as wait upon the Lord;</hi> whoſe hearts I deſire may bee raiſed up with ſtrength to wait further on him, but I dare not preſume upon your patience too farre, therefore I ſay no more in it, then what the Lord hath ſaid in my Text, <hi>All you that truſt in the Lord, bee ſtrong:</hi> and know for certain, that <hi>God will ſtrengthen your hearts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>You have heard the particulars conſiderable in the Text,<note place="margin">Applic. to the Parliament.</note> and in generall how they meet with many by way of juſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proofe; as alſo how they may ſerve for the quickning of ſome, and raiſing up of others with comfort. Now give mee leave
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:154626:16"/>with <hi>Your</hi> patience to bring home all by a more particular ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, to all you that ſtand here this day before the Lord: In the firſt place (Honorable and dearely beloved in the Lord) my deſire is (with all due reſpect to your great and weighty imployments, and your perſonall worth) to point forth un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to You in a word or two, the way to the true valour mention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in my Text, well beſeeming ſuch as are ingaged <hi>in the cauſe of the Lord;</hi> that God may ſtrengthen your hearts, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably crowne your great employments with a happy and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired iſſue in the end: for this cauſe conſider, I beſeech you: Firſt, what God hath called you unto: Secondly, what he now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires to be done by you, whileſt you are ſtrugling to advance that worke: both which being cloſely followed, you may expect of the Lord both preſent comfort, and a happy cloſure of your juſt undertakings.</p>
            <p>Firſt, caſt your eyes upon your preſent employment, (which I crave may be weighed by you in the ballance of the ſanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry.) The <hi>work you</hi> are now called to, is a work of great concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it is <hi>the purging of the Lords floore:</hi> as it hath reference both to the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Common-wealth;</hi> a <hi>work</hi> ſure enough to be encountred with great oppoſitions: yet I muſt ſay, it is a <hi>worke,</hi> with the managing whereof God hath not ſo ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noured others, which have gone before you in your places: but hath reſerved it to make you the inſtruments of his glory in advancing it; and that doth much adde unto your honour: Was it an honour to the <hi>Tyrians,</hi> that they were counted amongſt the builders of the <hi>Temple,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezek. 28.</note> when <hi>Hiram</hi> ſent to <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomon</hi> things neceſſary for that worke? how then hath God honoured you, reſerving to you the care of re-edifying of his Church <hi>(the houſe of the living God)</hi> and the repairing of the ſhattered Common-wealth, (ſo farre borne downe before he raiſed you up to ſupport it) that ſucceeding ages may with honour to your names, ſay, THIS WAS THE RE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FORMING PARLIAMENT? A <hi>worke,</hi> which God by his bleſſing upon Your unwearied paines hath much furthered already: whileſt he by you hath removed the rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſh that might hinder the raiſing up of that goodly ſtructure appointed and preſcribed by the Lord in his word. Laſtly, <hi>a
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:154626:16"/>worke</hi> which God never in any age perfected but through ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny difficulties to his people.</p>
            <p>This is the worke <hi>You</hi> are called to; then let me ſay to <hi>You</hi> in the words of my Text, <hi>be ſtrong and of good courage, the Lord will ſtrengthen your hearts:</hi> and would <hi>You</hi> have <hi>Your</hi> hearts fortified with this ſoveraigne cordiall? then ſee you follow what the Lord requires of men imployed by him in ſuch a work, that you ſtriving to that, may attaine unto the other. For this cauſe let me in the name of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> (in whoſe name, <hi>by Your command,</hi> I ſtand now before <hi>You</hi>) crave of <hi>you</hi> to ſee to your carriage: Firſt, as <hi>you</hi> are Chriſtians: Secondly, as <hi>You</hi> are publick perſons entruſted with the managing of the Lords worke.</p>
            <p>Firſt, as You are Chriſtians, ſo have You need of courage: and if you would have your hearts ſtrengthened with it, then in your thoughts looke backe againe to that which was ſpoken in our ſecond propoſition; to wit, keepe to the work to which you are called: let not your hearts be carried on in the confidence of your own parts, but reſt upon the Lord for his ſtrength: ſee how God hath carried you through many ſtraights alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, and learne to depend on him for the future, committing the ſucceſſe of all to his wiſdome and goodneſſe: to all which I humbly pray, remember that as you appeare for the <hi>truth,</hi> ſo you muſt ſtick to it: Firſt, in the profeſſion: Secondly, in the practiſe of it. <hi>Truth</hi> ſhould be deare to all that profeſſe it; the <hi>truth</hi> which is brought from heaven by the <hi>Lord Jeſus Chriſt, the word of his Father,</hi> which he hath ſealed with his bloud: <hi>the truth,</hi> the profeſſion whereof hath beene watered with the bloud of your <hi>Noble Anceſtors</hi> that have gone before you: for this <hi>truth,</hi> let me ſpake to you in the words of holy <hi>Jude, and exhort you to contend earneſtly for the ſame:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Jude 3.</note> love to the <hi>truth,</hi> and well ordered zeale for the ſame, well beſeem's all that profeſſe the <hi>truth,</hi> eſpecially ſuch as are in authority and high places of dignity; though the world judge it a thing beneath great places: therefore if any queſtion about it ſhould be raiſed up before you, albeit the world would perſwade you to be of <hi>Galli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> his mind, who cared for <hi>none of theſe things;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 18.17.</note> yet I pray take notice, that the God of truth hath led men in
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:154626:17"/>authority to higher thoughts of it; which hath made them ſticke cloſer to it, then with a lukewarme diſpoſition to ſtand by and ſee it trodden down: was it not commanded by the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Edict of the Emperour <hi>Juſtinus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>that no man ſhould bee ſuffered ſo farre as to change one ſyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lable of the Orthodox Doctrine of the Church, in the myſtery of the ſacred Trinity?</hi> &amp; why? <hi>becauſe the Verity of the Chriſtian Faith was comprehended in the words and ſyllables.</hi> Wee know alſo what ſtirres Satan raiſed up in the Church about one Letter, in oppoſing of the Truth; whileſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> was cryed down by the <hi>Arians,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> pleaded againſt by the famous Lights of the Church. When the <hi>Emperours De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puty</hi> dealt with <hi>Baſil</hi> the great, to enter into communion with <hi>Budoxius,</hi> hee anſwered with reſolution,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>That none trained up in holy Scriptures would ſuffer one ſyllable of divine truths, to bee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed: but were ready (if it were required) to ſuffer any death in the defence thereof:</hi> here are precedents worthy of your imitation, to raiſe up your hearts to ſhine before others in the cloſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the truth: and the rather, becauſe ſuch is the waxy diſpoſition of the people, that the example of ſuperiours ever makes a deep impreſſion upon them, either in cleaving to the <hi>Truth,</hi> or departing from it: for if ſuch as are heads to others, bee not well-affected to the <hi>Truth,</hi> what can bee expected of their followers? the Books of <hi>Kings,</hi> and <hi>Chronicles,</hi> in <hi>Judah</hi> and <hi>Iſrael</hi> do tell us, the people are ever carryed on by the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of their Governours: when either they cleaved to the Truth, or turned their backs upon the ſame; ſo went the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the people, either for, or againſt it; and ſo fell it out in the Chriſtian Church; how was the Eaſterne Empire polluted with execrable <hi>Arianiſme,</hi> whilſt yet the Weſterne continued in the <hi>Truth?</hi> the Hiſtorians give the reaſon of it. <hi>Conſtantine</hi> an <hi>Arian</hi> ruled in the Eaſt; when at the ſame time <hi>Conſtans</hi> and <hi>Conſtantius</hi> Sonnes to <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Great, tread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:154626:17"/>in the ſteps of their pious father adhered to the truth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed by him, and ſo did as farre ennoble the weſterne Empire with the truth, as the other did defile the eaſterne with his countenancing of error and hereſie: I ſpare to bring forth before <hi>you</hi> other inſtances, eſpecially ſpeaking to ſuch as are not ignorant of any thing I can produce; onely let mee renew my humble motion unto <hi>you:</hi> Set your hearts to ſtand for the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion of the <hi>truth,</hi> if you would have the God of truth to fill <hi>you with courage</hi> firmely by your endeavors to ſettle his truth amongſt us.</p>
            <p>In the next place the man that would bee valorous for the truth, muſt looke as well to his practiſe as to the profeſſion of the truth; <hi>the truth</hi> muſt bee held out before the world in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, and a holy practiſe muſt warrantably evidence <hi>the life and power</hi> of that profeſſion: for ſeeing God hath coupled theſe together, profeſſion and practiſe of the truth; no man muſt ſeek to part them in himſelfe; bee <hi>you</hi> then holy men in <hi>your practiſe,</hi> you profeſſe to all the world this day; the Nation reſts aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of <hi>you,</hi> that you ſeeke to advance the cauſe of a holy God: your ſolemne <hi>Covenant</hi> into which you have lately entred tells the world, that it is your deliberate reſolution not onely <hi>to preſerve and reforme Religion, &amp;c.</hi> but you have alſo <hi>profeſſed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore God and the world your deſires to bee humbled for your owne ſins, and for the ſinnes of the Kingdome, and</hi> you have teſtified, <hi>that it is your unfained deſire and purpoſe to amend your lives, and to ſtrive each one to goe before another in the example of a reall reformation, &amp;c.</hi> are not theſe ſolemne promiſes ſtrong engagements to oblige <hi>you</hi> to a holy and cloſe walking with your God, whom you profeſſe to know, and promiſe to ſerve? hee that ſtands for <hi>pietie</hi> and is not pious, (God knowes) doth not a little weaken the cauſe of <hi>pietie</hi> whilſt hee ſeeks to advance it. It is ſtoried of <hi>Juſtinus</hi> the ſecond, that hee defended the orthodox faith, not onely amongſt his owne Subjects againſt hereticall pravity, but alſo hee aided forraine Chriſtians againſt the injuries they ſuſtained of others; (for hee had warre with the Perſians in their defence) O but what of all this? his ſinfull life defiled with pleaſures, with covetouſneſſe, with crueltie againſt his owne blood, &amp;c. with the durt of theſe ſinfull courſes was his
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:154626:18"/>defence of the truth eclipſed, ſtained, and obſcured; yea, and hee ſmarted for it. <hi>Honorable Worthies,</hi> this I ſpeake to encourage you in the way of a holy practiſe: you know what was ſaid of old,</p>
            <q>
               <l>Qui monet ut facias, quod jam facis, ipſe monendo</l>
               <l>Laudat, &amp; hortatu comprobat acta ſuo.</l>
            </q>
            <p>This I ſpeake to ſtirre <hi>up your holy minds</hi> to aſpire more and more by your religious lives to beautifie and adorne the holy cauſe of <hi>Religion</hi> for which you appeare this day: did the Lord <hi>require holineſſe of his people,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſs. 52.11</note> 
               <hi>who carried the veſſells of the Lord?</hi> (which was ſpoken of the time in which they were to carry backe from <hi>Babylon</hi> the veſſels of the Lords houſe taken away by <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> before) O then what holineſſe will the Lord require of <hi>you</hi> that ſtand up to carry on the holy worke of the holy God? when <hi>your</hi> exemplary holineſſe layes open the way to others in the practiſe thereof in your ſelves, if they be not wonne by your example to follow it, then have you quit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted your owne ſoules, and they are left without excuſe, when you have laboured to have truth held forth to them as a guide, and followed it in your owne practiſe: O that it might bee ſaid of all you in your houſes as of that pious Emperor <hi>Theodoſius the younger: cujus regia non diſſimilis crat monaſterio:</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> in the morning his cuſtome was to ſing Pſalmes unto the Lord; hee was ſo well inſtructed in the Scriptures that hee could diſcourſe of them with the Biſhops as if hee had beene one himſelfe; hee was not given to unadviſed anger nor baſe revenge (impotent paſſions too uſually attending upon greatneſſe.) In the pious ordering of his perſonall carriage, and family, hee had a war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rantable precedent before his time, even <hi>Conſtant. M.</hi> whoſe <hi>Court was as a Church for pietie;</hi> (ſo ſaith the Hiſtorian that pens his life) it was his cuſtome to call his family together, read the ſacred Scriptures to them, and pray with them; by which meanes was his royall Palace, together with his Comtiers and Souldiers, inured to holineſſe, and breathed after Chriſt; yea ſuch as were not ſound in the truth were yet convinced by his practiſe. Here are precedents worthy to bee followed by you; great men, men of eminent place, even Emperours had ſo lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:154626:18"/>Chriſt, as not to bee aſhamed to bee eminent for the pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of pietie, as well as for worldly government. It was not deemed in thoſe dayes a ſchiſmaticall and unwarrantable pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe unbeſeeming greatneſſe, for great men, and potentates to ſtudie to bee pious themſelves, and to promote godlineſſe in their charges; ſo doe <hi>you,</hi> and God will ſill <hi>you</hi> with courage to fulfill what hee requires of <hi>you</hi> in <hi>your</hi> places; an unholy heart may boaſt of God, but can never bee truely bold for God and goodneſſe: the guiltie conſcience will occaſion feares, which will daunt courage when it is moſt required, moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary, and uſefull: therefore as <hi>you are Chriſtians</hi> follow ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe in your profeſſion and practiſe, which will raiſe up your hearts with that courage which cannot eaſily bee quelled.</p>
            <p>But I muſt ſpeake further to <hi>you</hi> in another capacitie, as <hi>you</hi> are publicke perſons ſharing in that <hi>legiſllative</hi> power, which hath influence upon the whole kingdome: to the faithfull diſcharge of which condition courage is more requiſite then to the former (as you are Chriſtian men:) for if any bee ſure to bee oppoſed, it is men called out to rule and governe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; and if courage bee conducing to the well ordering of any calling, it is to the Magiſtrates in the firſt place; hence is it, that amongſt the meete qualifications of an able Ruler, in <hi>Jethro</hi> his judgment courage is ranked in the firſt place, <hi>Ex.</hi> 18. Now that <hi>you</hi> may attaine to it in this capacitie in which <hi>you</hi> ſtand at preſent, I ſhall commend unto you ſoure things whch are proper to <hi>you</hi> in your <hi>legiſllative</hi> ſtation. 1. Make no Lawes againſt Religion and pietie; 2. Recall ſuch as have been made in the times of ignorance againſt the ſame; 3. Study to uphold and maintaine ſuch profitable and wholeſome Lawes as have been formerly enacted for God and his people; 4. Improve what was well begun by others before <hi>you,</hi> and not perfected by them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the Governour, who deſires to manage his authoritie with courage and comfort, muſt beware hee give no conſent, or have no hand in the enacting of a Law that makes againſt God or his cauſe; for ſuch never proſpered.<note place="margin">Dan. 6.</note> The Rulers and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours ſollicited King <hi>Darius</hi> to make a law &amp; decree, which
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:154626:19"/>was derogatory to the glory of God, as it was invented for a ſnare to <hi>Daniel,</hi> and have you not read how they ſped? Did not this among other things adde to <hi>Conſtant. M.</hi> his renoune? though in all things his care was to advance divine worſhip, <hi>tamen in legibus condendis vel maxime.</hi> Eminent governours have ſtained the glory of their government by enacting Lawes which ſtand in oppoſition to Gods Law: <hi>Valentinian</hi> the great beginning to alienate his affection from his royall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſort (the cauſe I ſpare to relate) caſting his affection upon <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtina,</hi> thereupon makes it free by Law for any, that would, to have two wives, and after the promulgation of that Law pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently he married her: how inconſiſtent his Law was with the Law of God, I need not ſpeake.</p>
            <p>Secondly, goe farther, if the times of former ignorance have led your <hi>Noble Anceſtors</hi> to decree and publiſh any Law repug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant to godlineſſe, make haſt to repeale ſuch, as well as others, which in your grave judgements you find dangerous to the preſent ſtate of the commonwealth. There were two grand evills countenanced by Law in <hi>Rome</hi> before <hi>Theodoſius</hi> came thither, and both ſuppreſſed by his religious care; the one was the putting downe of filthy houſes, neſts of uncleanneſſe; the other was about preventing of murder and other miſde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meanors frequently acted in their common baking houſes: though both theſe evills had the countenence of Law before, hee ſuppreſſed them by enacting Lawes to the contrary; here were evill Lawes piouſly by his care repealed: ſo doe you, and God ſhall fill you with holy courage to enable you for your worke.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, labour to maintaine that, which by the pietie and holy zeale of <hi>your Anceſtors</hi> before <hi>you</hi> hath beene warrantably enacted for Religion and the Common-wealth. <hi>Non minor eſt virtus, quam quaerere, parta tueri:</hi> herein failed the Princes and Governours in <hi>Jeboaſh</hi> time, who continued not what was well ſetled by <hi>Jehojada</hi> whilſt hee lived,<note place="margin">2 Chro. 24.</note> 
               <hi>but left the houſe of the Lord God of their fathers and ſerved groves and Idols, and wrath came up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Judah, becauſe of their treſpaſſe;</hi> you ſee where they failed, and how they were rewarded; What a bane was it to this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, when the States of the Kingdom in Parliament agreed to
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:154626:19"/>revoke the wholeſome Lawes enacted in the raigne of that pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Prince <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixth againſt the Idolatry and ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Rome?</hi> was it not the cauſe of the effuſion of the preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous blood of ſo many <hi>Martyrs</hi> afterwards; whereof I feare the nation is not cleanſed to this day? and whence came the flood of the late innovations which defaced the Church (famous a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong other Churches before) but onely from hence; for not maintaining the vigour of former Lawes then a foote, but careleſly paſt over, or perverſly wreſted by ſuch, as ſhould have kept them up in their ſtrength? If the Lord in former a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges hath directed them that went before <hi>you</hi> in this place to ſtrengthen Religion and ſupport the Common-wealth; doe <hi>you</hi> in <hi>your</hi> times keepe up thoſe Lawes: then will the Lord af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ford you courage to defend them, and <hi>your ſelves</hi> and us by them. When <hi>Theodoſius</hi> the Great ſet forth a Law among the Egyptians againſt the ſacrificing to the River <hi>Nilus,</hi> it ſo fell out that the River that yeare did not riſe to the uſuall height in overflowing of the land; this the heathen aſcribed to their not ſacrificing to it, and ſo begun to blame the imperiall edict: the governour fearing ſome inſurrection or tumult would enſue, gave timely information to the Emperour hereof; withall im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying that hee could have beene content to have had the <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour</hi> connived at them for that time: but the holy <hi>Emperour</hi> anſwered re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>that it was better to remaine faithfull to the Lord, then to preferre the overflowing of Nilus and the expectation of fruitfulneſſe thereby to pietie, yea hee would rather it ſhould never overflow a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, &amp;c.</hi> Here was a Law ſeaſonably declared, and an heroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call reſolution, that would not upon any pretence whatſoever give way to repeale that Law that was conformable to Gods Word: with the like courage ought faithfull Magiſtrates to maintaine warrantable Lawes for Gods honour in defence of that which is good in Gods ſight, and by no meanes bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to ſinne againſt God either under hope of gaine, or feare of approching danger, to let thoſe Lawes ſinke, whereby reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and the Commonwealth have beene upheld.</p>
            <pb n="34" facs="tcp:154626:20"/>
            <p> Fourthly, to improve what hath been well begun by your <hi>Anceſtors</hi> for the Lord and his cauſe; and the rather, becauſe no reformation can riſe to its perfection at the firſt: How long was the Temple in building after the people returned from their captivitie? yet was the worke perfected in the end: it was <hi>Nehemiahs</hi> honour to carry it on to that degree; hee that ſhall duely weigh with himſelfe either the firſt planting of a Church where it was not, or the reforming of it, when once it was planted and afterwards defiled; hee that ſhall ſeriouſly weigh either of theſe workes, will eaſily grant it is not the worke of one time to bring a Church to perfection, and muſt conclude that many oppoſitions muſt attend upon both theſe, before a great building can bee reared up, or a goodly decaying ſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture reedified: is there not much adoe, are there not great ſtones to bee digged out of the earth which muſt bee ſmoothed ere they can be coupled together in the building? ſo what adoe had the bleſſed Apoſtles (the maſter builders of the Church) to lay the foundations of particular Churches, whilſt the devill and the world and all their united forces laboured to with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it? and when particular Churches were planted, how ſoone came they to be corrupted and peſtered with tares in one kind or another? I neede not give you inſtances to make out this truth, every one to whom the ſtory of the Scripture is knowne, will ſubſcribe unto it; is there not then courage re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of them that are engaged in the great worke of reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Church? and have they not need to obſerve how farre ſuch as have gone before have carried on the worke, and ſtudie to improve it?</p>
            <p>Thus have I adventured to bring forth before you ſome ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neralls proper to your <hi>legiſlative</hi> ſtation: I dare not deſcend to the particular Lawes neceſſary to bee enacted, repealed, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held, or improved, that being above my reach, and without my ſphere: onely I crave freedome to quicken you in impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving what hath been enacted by your <hi>Noble Anceſtors</hi> for the due obſervation of two of Gods ſacred ordinances; for which ſome lawes have beene declared, but proviſion for the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full keeping of them hath not beene made: I meane againſt the horrible abuſe of <hi>the holy Sacrament of the Lords Supper,</hi> and the
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:154626:20"/>irreligious profanation of the <hi>Lords day:</hi> (both which in the Scriptures have the honour of the <hi>Lords name</hi> put unto them,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> Revel. 1.10. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, 1 Cor. 11.20.</note> which no other ordinance in all the new Teſtament hath) ſome Lawes I confeſſe have beene enacted in this State againſt both theſe diſorders: but (God knowes) they have not beene fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed with that powerfull vigor with which they ſhould have beene quickned. It was once by Law provided <hi>if any re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pairing to the holy Communion were an open and notorious evill liver, ſo that the congregation by him is offended; the Curate having know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge thereof ſhall call him, and advertiſe him in any wiſe not to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume to the Lords Table, untill hee hath openly declared himſelfe to have truely repented, and amended his former naughtie life: that the Congregation might thereby bee ſatisfied, which afore were offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, &amp;c.</hi> Here was proviſion againſt the pollution of the ſacred <hi>Euchariſt;</hi> but (alas!) the poore <hi>Miniſter</hi> of the Goſpell was not ſtrengthned to doe it: whereupon it came to paſſe that (ſuch as tooke upon them the ſole adminiſtration of all eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſticall diſcipline, and yet <hi>lived on the ſinnes of the people</hi>) our Courts ſtripping the Miniſters, and <hi>Guardians of the Church</hi> of that power, engroſt it to themſelves: whereby a door was ever kept open to profane men to approach to that holy Table even inſpite of any conſcientious miniſter of the Goſpel; which gave occaſion to many to keep off from approaching to it, whilſt they ſaw ſuch to be admitted to the participation of it: and this theſe courts durſt doe notwithſtanding the former Law, though it was otherwiſe provided of old, when <hi>by the diſcipline of the Church,</hi>
               <note place="margin">In eccleſia ſolent a Sacramentis al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taris viſibilibus homine<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> diſtipli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na eccleſiaſtica removeri.</note> 
               <hi>ſuch were denied the participatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of that holy Sacrament and not admitted to it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The other evill (declared by <hi>Law</hi> to be forbidden) is the prophanation of <hi>the Lords day:</hi> againſt which the prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of our age may juſtly challenge at <hi>your hands</hi> a quickening of theſe Lawes to ſuppreſſe that <hi>crying ſinne.</hi> I have obſerved from the ſyſteme of your Lawes, that in former ages ſome things have beene enacted in <hi>this State</hi> againſt that evill alſo: for by publick <hi>authority Fairs have beene put off from that day, no Court to be kept on it: Taylors and Shoomakers have beene for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidden to carry home their ware to their cuſtomers on that day;
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:154626:21"/>ſome ſports likewiſe have beene forbidden on it, &amp;c.</hi> here were good be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginnings of a Reformation, which ſhould be improved to the better ſolemniſing of that day: O but if you (Honoured Senators) would be pleaſed to theſe reſtraints to adde more, whereby ſuch in whom conſcience of their duty is leſſe pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfull, might be kept off from prophaning of that time which ſhould <hi>be conſecrattd as a delight and holy unto the Lord:</hi> how ſhould you endeare your ſelves unto the Lord, and be honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with renowne in his Church? and I beſeech you, doth not our preſent condition require this at your hands? When <hi>Guntbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ramnus</hi> perceived the glory of his Kingdome to be abated, and the unhappy ſucceſſe of his warres with the <hi>Gothes:</hi> whileſt he enquired after the cauſes hereof and ſought for a remedy; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt other things, <hi>hee reproves the prophaneneſſe of his Clergie, and their careleſneſſe in not feeding the people committed to their charge:</hi> then he layes this as a foundation for the remedying of thoſe evils,<note place="margin">Diem Domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum religioſe cuſt odiendum eſſe.</note> appointing <hi>that the Lords day ſhould be religiouſly kept.</hi> So doe you, and we may be aſſured with more confidence that God will haſten the cloſure of our unnaturall warres. Let it not be judged boldneſſe in mee to remember you hereof. Was it not once appointed,<note place="margin">
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>t humiliter a ſacerdotibus Chriſtianorum exeellentia fla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitetur: ut ob honorem, et re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verentiam tanti diei cunct is me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum injiciant, ne in tam ſancto<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> die mercatus, placita et opera ſua homines fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere praeſumant.</note> 
               <hi>that Chriſtian Magiſtrates ſhould be humbly ſued unto by the Miniſters; that for the honour and reverence of ſo great a day Magiſtrates ſhould make all afraid, that they preſume not to follow their Merchandiſe, pleaſures, or other workes on that holy day?</hi> ſpeaking of the Lords day. Theſe are the two evils, the remedy whereof Law hath begun: O that God would ſtirre up your hearts to improve both! So ſhould the Lord delight in us, honour you, and haſten the deſired end to our heavy and waſting troubles.</p>
            <p>Know then in a word all you whom God hath ranked in that honourable ſtation to give lawes unto others: it is your part to ſee that nothing be enacted againſt God, to repeal whatſoever of that kinde the ignorance of former times hath agreed unto, to maintaine what hath beene worthily conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded before your times, and to improve that which they hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily begunne, but by the iniquity of the times could not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect: this is the duty which God requires of you, and thus walking and waiting on God, <hi>be ſtrong and the Lord will ſtrengthen your hearts.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:154626:21"/>
            <p> Now a few words more to you (men, fathers and bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren) who likewiſe appeare before the Lord this day to heare what he will ſpeak unto you from his word: you have neede alſo to be encouraged in your places to waite upon the Lord, that he may ſtrengthen your hearts in defence of his cauſe: <hi>Deborah</hi> her heart was not onely upon the <hi>heads and governours of Iſrael;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Judg. 5.</note> but alſo on all among the people, who went forth with cheerefulneſſe againſt the common enemy of their Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion and Peace: Would you be encouraged by God? then make knowne your courage in comming forth to appeare for your <hi>Honourable heads and governours,</hi> who ſtand for God, his truth, and your liberties. Shall the upholding of <hi>Religion</hi> to you and your poſterity be dearer to our <hi>ever-honoured Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies,</hi> then their owne lives and eſtates? and will not you ſhew courage in cleaving to them in your juſt defence? ſhall the ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers with <hi>Joab</hi> arme themſelves with brave reſolutions <hi>to be valiant for God, for their people and the Cities of their God?</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 10.12.</note> and ſhall the men of the City not be valorous for their City and them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves? God forbid: And I beſeech you diſcover your holy va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lour, firſt in wreſtling with the Lord by fervent prayer on their behalfe, that they may carry on the worke of Reformation now in hand: ſhould not your ſpirits be rouſed up to follow God with the ſweete incenſe of your continuall requells to God for his bleſſing upon this work? what though it be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rided by the jibing <hi>Iſhmaelites,</hi> and withſtood by the Gyant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like <hi>Anakims</hi> of our age? yet faithfull prayer (that can o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the windowes of heaven, and draw downe raine from thence) can remove theſe mountaines, and levell the way be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them to advance the worke: holy <hi>Ezra</hi> was aſhamed to ſolicite an Army of the King to guard him and ſuch as retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with him; but reſolves to commit all to God:<note place="margin">Ezra <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.21.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> therefore he (did as we doe this day) ſought God by prayer attended with faſting; and happy was the iſſue. Earneſtly prayer is knowne to have done that which ſtrength and policy could not doe. When that unworthy heretick <hi>Arius</hi> was incenſed againſt <hi>Alexander</hi> becauſe he would not receive him into com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with him, <hi>Euſebius</hi> (the upholder of <hi>Arius</hi>) threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <hi>Aelxander that by ſuch a day be ſhould be caſt from his place, ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed,
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:154626:22"/>and his ſucceſſor would admit</hi> Arius <hi>into Church-fellow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip with him:</hi> the day before that ſhould fall out, holy <hi>Alex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ander</hi> goes into the Church, falls downe upon the ground and continued with all ardency of affection powring forth his earneſt prayer to the Lord to fruſtrate the attempts of his enemies: and would you know what was the fruit of his powerfull prayer? in the evening of that day <hi>Arius</hi> was taken away by an execrable judgement in his ſudden death: prayer faithfully performed is never without effect, it is of a prevai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling power with God: be perſwaded therefore to follow God with prayer for his bleſſing upon the publick work now in hand: ever knowing that the more you are taken up with effectuall prayer, the more courage will the Lord infuſe into your hearts: a praying heart will be bold as a Lyon.</p>
            <p>Secondly, let your courage for the Lord appeare in furthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring his work with that eſtate with which the Lord hath bleſſed you: aſſuredly for my part, I muſt ſay of many of you and of your forwardneſſe herein, as the Apoſtle once ſpake of the <hi>Macedonians;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Cor. 8.3, 11.</note> 
               <hi>who were willing to their power</hi> to further Gods cauſe in the reliefe of his members: I may ſay further with him,<note place="margin">2 Cor. 9.</note> 
               <hi>that your zeale hath provoked many:</hi> ſo many have had their hearts enflamed to further Gods work by your rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſſe to ſupport the ſame: all that I ſay herein is onely this, conſider that the worke is great, and many withdraw their helpe; yet goe you on with cheerefulneſſe, though the charge be great, it will quit all the coſt when God ſhall give you or yours to ſee <hi>Zion</hi> raiſed up in beauty.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, if God call any of you to be an inſtrument in your places to further the work, let your hearts be filled with courage, and your hands active with all faithfulneſſe to fulfill what in required of you in your Sphere: many other things I might adde as ingredients into this cordiall for raiſing up your hearts with courage to waite upon the Lord; but I ſhall conclude all as I begun;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Be of good courage, the Lord ſhall ſtrengthen your hearts all you that waite upon the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:154626:22"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
